# Long Wang

Contact Department of Systems Engineering and Engineering Management, Email:

Information City University of Hong Kong, long.wang@my.cityu.edu.hk

88 Tat Chee Ave, Kowloon Tong, Mobile Phone: Hong Kong  $+852\ 68560751$ 

Research Interests I am interested in machine learning, computer vision and their applications in renewable energy. I have focused on developing deep learning based anomaly detection approaches for complex systems, such as wind turbines. Meanwhile, I have worked on developing computer vision algorithms for object detection based on UAV-taken images.

**EDUCATION** City University of Hong Kong

2014-present\*

Ph.D. in Systems Engineering and Engineering Management Supervisor: Dr. Zijun Zhang

\*Expected graduation date: October 2017

University College London (UCL) 2013-2014

Dissertation Supervisor: Dr. Kevin Bryson M.Sc. in Computer Science, Distinction

China Agricultural University 2011-2013

M.Eng. in Hydraulic Engineering Supervisor: Professor Peiling Yang

China Agricultural University

2007-2011

B.Eng. in Irrigation and Drainage Engineering, GPA: 3.81/4.00

| Awards and   | Hong Kong PhD Fellowship     | 2014 - 2017 |
|--------------|------------------------------|-------------|
| SCHOLARSHIPS | Research Tuition Scholarship | 2015-2016   |

2014-2015 Chow Yei Ching School of Graduate Studies Entrance Scholarships Outstanding Graduates of Beijing 2013 Outstanding Graduates of China Agricultural University 2013 Excellent All-round Student of Beijing 2011 First Class Scholarship for Academic Excellence 2010 Excellent All-round Student of China Agricultural University 2010 Samsung Scholarship for Agricultural Talents 2010Second Class Scholarship for Academic Excellence 2009 Excellent All-round Student of China Agricultural University 2009 National Encouragement Scholarship 2009 First Class Scholarship for Academic Excellence 2008

Excellent All-round Student of China Agricultural University 2008

National Encouragement Scholarship 2008

# RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

# Integration of Machine Learning and Computational Intelligence

2016-Present

Advisors: Prof. Henry Chung, Prof. Alain Bensoussan, and Dr. Zijun Zhang

The goal of this project is to develop a regression model guided swarm intelligence algorithm. We are working on integrating the Gaussian process model into a swarm intelligence algorithm and thus the Gaussian process model is utilized for estimating the fitness function values. This algorithm has been applied to track the maximum power point of PV systems.

#### GPU-based Parallel Jaya Algorithm

2016-Present

Advisor: Dr. Zijun Zhang

This project aims to develop a parallel Jaya algorithm implemented on GPU. Compared with the conventional Jaya algorithm, the parallel Jaya algorithm is also free of any algorithm-specific parameters and the three main procedures, solution update, fitness value computation, and the best/worst solution selection are all computed in parallel on GPU. We have applied this algorithm to estimate parameters of a li-ion battery model.

#### Object Detection Using UAVs

2015-Present

Advisor: Dr. Zijun Zhang

Objection detection algorithms are highly desired in emerging applications of UAVs for remote inspection tasks. We are working on designing an improved cascading classifier for objection detection based on UAV-taken images. In order to reduce the number of features utilized, decision trees and support vector machines are utilized as substitutions of boosting algorithms. This algorithm has been applied for detecting surface cracks on wind turbine blades.

#### **Anomaly Detection of Complex Systems**

2014-Present

Advisor: Dr. Zijun Zhang

This project aims at developing data-driven anomaly detection approaches for complex systems. We are working on developing deep learning based frameworks to detection anomalies of complex systems. In these frameworks, deep learning algorithms, such as deep autoencoders and dropout deep neural networks, are employed to model complex systems while statistical control charts are utilized to monitor the abnormal statuses. We have applied these frameworks for wind turbine condition monitoring and fault diagnosis.

#### Short-term Electricity Price Forecasting

2014-2015

Advisor: Dr. Zijun Zhang

Developed an extended stacked denoising autoencoders model, which incorporates both the stochastic neighbor embedding and the random sample consensus algorithms. This model has outperformed classical data-driven models and an industrial method in forecasting electricity prices of five hubs in the USA.

# Work Experience

#### City University of Hong Kong

#### Teaching Assistant

2015-2016

Duties at various times have included teaching tutorials, office hours, and leading weekly computer lab exercises.

Postgraduate Level:

• SEEM 6015 Supply Chain Management, Semester A 2015/16, Class Size: 85

Undergraduate Level:

- SEEM 4025 Quality Systems & Management, Semester B 2015/16, Class Size: 30
- SEEM 3040 Engineering Database & Systems, Semester A 2016/17, Class Size: 18

# China Agricultural University

Research Assistant 2011-2013

Advisor: Prof. Peiling Yang

Developed a neural network based model to forecast soil moisture based on historical data and weather information.

Worked as the IT-supporter in the Soil-physics Lab

# China Longyuan Power Group Corporation Ltd., Beijing, China

Summer Intern Summer 2015

Mentor: Jia Xu

Developed and implemented a data-driven framework for monitoring wind turbine power generation performance

#### Parensoc Ltd., London, UK

Summer Intern Summer 2014

Mentor: Mital Kinderkhedia

Developed both the front-end and the back-end of a social networking website. The project included user interface design, database design, and friend recommendation algorithm development.

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

- **L. Wang** and Z. Zhang, "Automatic Detection of Wind Turbine Blade Surface Cracks Based on UAV-taken Images," *IEEE Transactions on Industrial Electronics*, accepted, 2017.
- S. Jang, K.S. Chin, **L. Wang**, G. Qu, and K.L. Tsui, "Modified Genetic Algorithm-based Feature Selection Combined with Pre-trained Deep Neural Network for Demand Forecasting in Outpatient Department," *Expert Systems with Applications*, accepted, 2017.
- **L. Wang**, Z. Zhang, and J. Chen, "Short-term Electricity Price Forecasting with Stacked Denoising Autoencoders," *IEEE Transactions on Power Systems*, accepted, 2016.
- **L. Wang**, Z. Zhang, J. Xu, and R. Liu, "Wind Turbine Blade Breakage Monitoring with Deep Autoencoders," *IEEE Transactions on Smart Grid*, accepted, 2016.
- L. Wang, Z. Zhang, H. Long, J. Xu, and R. Liu, "Wind Turbine Gearbox Failure Identification with Deep Neural Networks," *IEEE Transactions on Industrial Informatics*, accepted, 2016.
- **L. Wang**, H. Long, Z. Zhang, J. Xu, and R. Liu, "Wind Turbine Gearbox Failure Monitoring Based on SCADA Data Analysis," *2016 IEEE Power and Energy Society General Meeting*, Boston, MA, July 2016.
- H. Long, L. Wang, Z. Zhang, Z. Song, and J. Xu, "Data-Driven Wind Turbine Power Generation Performance Monitoring," *IEEE Transactions on Industrial Electronics*, vol. 62, no. 10, pp. 6627-6635, June 2015.

# SUBMITTED PAPERS

- **L. Wang**, C. Huang, Z. Zhang, and K.L. Tsui, "Estimation of Li-ion Battery Model Parameters with a GPU-accelerated Parallel Jaya Algorithm," *IEEE Transactions on Power Electronics*, under review.
- **L. Wang**, L. Zhuang, Z. Zhang, R.K.K. Yuen, and K.L. Tsui, "Automatic Detection of Rail Surface Crack with a Superpixel Based Data-driven Approach," *IEEE Transactions on Industrial Electronics*, under review.
- C. Huang, L. Wang, Z. Zhang, and A. Bensoussan, "A GPR Guided Jaya Algorithm for Maximum Power Point Tracking of PV Systems," *IEEE Transactions on Sustainable Energy*, under revision.

C. Huang, L. Wang, Z. Zhang, and A. Bensoussan, "The Point and Probabilistic Forecasting of Solar Radiations Based on Information of Neighboring Sites: A Data-Driven Study," *IEEE Transactions on Smart Grid*, under review.

#### Presentations

"Data-driven Wind Turbine Condition Monitoring," 2016 East Lake International Forum for Outstanding Overseas Young Scholars, December, 2016, Wuhan, China

"Data Mining and its Application to Wind Energy," China Longyuan Power Group Corporation Ltd., November, 2016, Beijing, China

"Wind Turbine Gearbox Failure Monitoring Based on SCADA Data Analysis," 2016 IEEE Power and Energy Society General Meeting, July 2016, Boston, USA

"Wind Turbine Gearbox Failure Monitoring Based on SCADA Data Analysis," Seminar Series, Department of Systems Engineering and Engineering Management, City University of Hong Kong, August, 2016, Hong Kong

"Data-driven Wind Turbine Generation Performance Monitoring," China Longyuan Power Group Corporation Ltd., August, 2015, Beijing, China

#### SOFTWARE

#### Sarky Grammaticus

Developers: Long Wang, Haoqiang Liu, and Jun Shang

This is a mobile game application (sponsored by Google UK) for Icelandic language learning, which supports multiple platforms including iOS and Android. An introduction video can be found at: https://youtu.be/VAVMbOHz\_h8.

## Professional

Member, IEEE & IEEE Power and Energy Society

ACTIVITIES

Member, Chinese Society for Electrical Engineering (CSEE)

Reviewer, Journal of Intelligent Manufacturing

Reviewer, IET Electronics Letters

Reviewer, The Open Electrical & Electronic Engineering Journal

Reviewer, IEEE Transactions on Cybernetics

# Computer Skills

Programming languages: Python, Java, R, JavaScript, PHP, MATLAB, Miranda, Visual Basic,

F#, C++, and Assembly

Libraries, APIs, or Frameworks: Theano, Pandas, OpenCV, Django, Bootstrap, and CUDA

Database Systems: MySQL, PostgreSQL, and Neo4j

Typesetting languages: LaTeX

#### References

#### Dr. Zijun Zhang, Assistant Professor

Department of Systems Engineering and Engineering Management, City University of Hong Kong P6618, Academic 1, City University of Hong Kong, Tat Chee Avenue, Hong Kong +(852)-3442-5328, zijzhang@cityu.edu.hk

#### Dr. Qingpeng Zhang, Assistant Professor

Department of Systems Engineering and Engineering Management, City University of Hong Kong P6608, Academic 1, City University of Hong Kong, Tat Chee Avenue, Hong Kong +(852)-3442-4727, qingpeng.zhang@cityu.edu.hk

# Prof. Kwok Leung Tsui, Chair Professor and Department Head

Department of Systems Engineering and Engineering Management, City University of Hong Kong P6622, Academic 1, City University of Hong Kong, Tat Chee Avenue, Hong Kong +(852)-3442-2177, kltsui@cityu.edu.hk